Stanford University
alright let's get back to su 3 and su 2
su 3 was QCD and it's the symmetry which
what did we say it acted vertically on
our table
it took us from one color red green and
blue and mix them up let's just let's
just remind ourselves about that so we
made ourselves a table this is a table
not of all elementary particles
obviously but it's table of all the
fermions yeah it's a table of all of the
fermions in the standard model and not
so much because they're fermions but
just happens that they're kind of the
constituents that's constituent
particles of the atom in the nucleus
all right so let's just write them down
again there were the six different
families of quarks the families refer to
well I'll tell you what they refer to
there's the up and down that's called a
family that's called the up/down family
then there is let's up down charm
strange I guess you can call it a charm
with a strange family and then there's
the top and the bottom
that's the horizontal structure and then
we have red green and blue and we have a
cork in each one of these slots let's
take this bar away here take this bar
away and take this one over here away we
have a cork in each one of these slots
and the color symmetry the su3 symmetry
color which is associated with quantum
chromodynamics is the symmetry group
which acts on this triplet here and
mixes them up into each other that
symmetry group has generators those
generators correspond to the infinitely
small transformations but it also
corresponds to the gluons the symmetry
group which takes red to green to blue
is associated with the existence of
gluons and the gluons when they're
emitted from one quark to another for
example from red to green you create a
red sorry red-green bar glue on this
transformation from red to green is
simply one of the generators of SU 3 so
the generators of SU 3 the
transformations are in one-to-one
correspondence with the emission of Ag
lawn you can think of an emission of a
glue on as a physical act which are
physical phenomenon which does the same
thing as the symmetry group which mixes
the particles into each other that's the
character of gauge bosons gauge bosons
are a sort of manifestation of the
symmetry group in which the emission of
a gauge boson really does change a a
particle from one
to another in exactly the same pattern
as the symmetry group would change one
thing to another all right so that's red
green and blue and when you perform one
of these transformations you do it on
all of the quarks simultaneously you
don't do it just in the up quarks or
just the up/down family if you want the
symmetry to be correct if you want it to
be a real symmetry of the theory then
you must do it simultaneously on all of
the quarks and that corresponds to the
statement that exactly the same glue on
ah let's say this is from up to up up
quark to up quark incidentally the glue
on emission does not change horizontally
it only changes vertically so for
example the same glue on which would be
involved in emitting or which would be
emitted when a red up quark becomes a
green up quark that's exactly the same
glue on as would be emitted when let's
say when a a top red quark would be a
top green quark red-green bar luan so
symmetry takes whole rows and mixes them
into each other then there was a second
symmetry by now it's actually a third
symmetry we've talked about
electrodynamics and what it does to the
what the emission of a photon or what
the what the symmetry associated with
electrodynamics is but now we're
encountering another symmetry which is
usually called flavor symmetry flavor
symmetry or I guess the family symmetry
somehow sometimes it takes ups to downs
at the same time that it takes charm to
strange at the same time
takes top to bottom bottom keeping the
color unchanged so for example there
will be processes in which an up quark
let's say of the blue variety emits a w+
boson which w+ and it becomes a down
quark also of the blue variety so what
has this W boson done it's a physical
manifestation of the transformation
which takes you horizontally back and
forth exactly the same w+ would mediate
or would be emitted the same kind of w+
would be emitted when a are green let's
say charm quark becomes a green strange
quark same w+ and so forth the gluons
never move your horizontally the W
bosons never move you vertically and
that is also the character of the
symmetry groups the symmetry groups move
your horizontally
that's su - it doesn't move you from
here to here or from here to here it
just moves you between up and down down
and up or at the same time charm and
strange strength to charm and so forth
that's the mathematical structure of SU
3 cross su 2 if you add the photon the
photon emission is associated with the
symmetry which changes the phase of
every charge carrying field which I
explained that to you last time every
charge carrying field transforms with a
phase under u1
and if you add those three together you
have the basic ingredients of su 3 cross
su 2 cross u 1 cross simply means that
it's a product structure where the su
twos don't mix up the colors and the su
threes don't mix up the upness and down
this one's a product structure and
that's where the terminology that's
where the I guess you call it
terminology that the standard model is a
gauge theory based on the gauge group su
3 cross su 2 cross u 1 now it is
actually a little bit more complicated
than I'm saying we're going to sort out
the complications but roughly speaking
su-34 color su 2 for the W emission and
u14 electrodynamics now this is good
it's going to get slightly more
complicated than that
because what I'm saying is not a hundred
percent consistent for reasons that will
become clear but not yet all right the
emission of a W boson incidentally of
course W bosons are only discovered
relatively late in the game and they
were postulated sometime in the 60s but
but it really only achieved some real
traction in 70s the W bosons but the
theory of weak interactions or some
aspects of the theory of weak
interactions goes back much earlier than
that I supposed to the 30s the family
theory of weak interactions and we'll
discuss the relationship soon enough
okay what about the coupling constants
that are involved in these various
interactions the u 1 coupling constant
here that's associated
the emission of a photon and the
coupling constant is simply the electric
charge the reason that the emission or
the reason that the probability of the
emission of a photon is the
fine-structure constant is because this
is the amplitude for the emission of a
photon you have to square it to find the
probability for the for the photon to be
present so e squared is basically the
fine-structure constant it has some PI's
and things that's not important but but
e squared is basically the
fine-structure constant and it's also
the coupling constant or the emission
the quantum mechanical amplitude for the
emission of a photon either the virtual
emission of a photon which means that
the photon is going to be reabsorbed
before it gets very far or if the
electron is jerked out of the way then
the real emission of a photon the
amplitude for that is this constant
called the electric charge and it's a
pure number and it's a number
well the fine-structure constant itself
the square of this number is as I told
you about 1 over 137 okay so it's a
small number or here the SU 3 coupling
constant that's usually called G or we
can call it G strong G sub s that of
course is associated with the emission
of a gluon and that's also a number that
number is close to warning well not
clear if that's a little one is a little
bit too big are the corresponding thing
corresponding to the fine-structure
constant would be more like about 1/5
1/5 is a lot bigger than a 1 over 137 so
the emission of a gluon is a much much
more probable event when a good when a
quark smacks into something
it basically emits a gluon with a
probability close to one almost always
emits a glue one whereas the photon
almost never emits a photon now you
might think in view of the fact that the
weak interactions are called very
weakened there are cold weak
interactions and in fact from the fact
that the decay rates are very much lower
associated with weak interactions the
weak interactions are indeed in many
many ways very much weaker than either
the glue onic interaction or the
electromagnetic interaction but it's not
because the coupling constant is smaller
the coupling constant of the weak
interactions is closely related to the
coupling constant for quantum
electrodynamics it's about the same
order of magnitude are related it's
related by some some simple numerical
factor but not the not very different so
that raises the question what is it
about these processes involving W bosons
that makes it so improbable so unlikely
that a weak interaction will take place
and it is unlikely after all it takes
the Neutron 12 minutes to decay it must
be a very unlikely process so that's the
next question let's think about the
decay of the neutron okay of the neutron
originates from a Down quark inside the
neutron down quark emitting a w- and
becoming an up quark so let's add in the
other quarks there's another down quark
and an up quark alright this is a
neutral oh sorry this is a neutron and
up and two downs and this is a proton -
ups and down and the W goes off that's W
- but then the W can also become W - can
become an electron and an anti-neutrino
ah let's go let's go back to this table
here let me remind you there are more
particles more fermions the additional
fermions are the leptons the leptons
come in basically the same pattern up
their charm strange top bottom but they
do not carry color the meaning of that
is they don't participate at all in the
color interactions now your first were
perfectly free to ask me why and I'm
perfectly free to say I don't know so
however there's a pattern and the
pattern is not it does have some
structure to it but I'll tell you what
not tonight but at some point maybe we
will understand this pattern better
almost as though it were a fourth color
are the leptons now the leptons do not
have the same charges as the quarks let
me just remind you these this column
would be the quarks with charge 2/3 and
this column would be the quarks we
charge minus 1/3 and notice that this
one has one more unit of charge than
this one the difference of charge is one
unit all right down in this lepton car
row over here the different the same is
true over here of course 2/3 minus 1/3
2/3 minus 1/3 now the emission of a
double you only cares about the
difference of charge
in other words allowed W can be emitted
if the difference of charge is the right
thing all right W plus or the W minus
has a definite charge
and to admit it the difference of charge
of the initial and final Fermi on must
be correct alright so if the W can be
emitted when a neutrino becomes an
electron or when it becomes an electron
becomes a neutrino the charge difference
must be the same okay
in fact what goes down here would be the
new to the neutrino the electron
neutrino and the electron the charge
difference is the same this has charge
minus one this has charge zero so the
charge difference is the same and it is
mathematically consistent to say that a
W boson the same W boson can be emitted
when a neutrino becomes an electron ah
in the next column under the charge
under the charm strange column comes the
anti the sorry the neutrino associated
with the muon and the muon
the muon is in every respect at least as
far as we know essentially the same as
the electron except its mass is about
200 times larger again no rhyme no
reason for that at the present time and
then under the top bottom column the
heaviest of the quarks is matched with
the heaviest of the electrons we
incidentally we don't know the details
of the masses of the neutrinos very well
all right this neutrino associated with
a towel lepton and the Tau lepton and
the Tau lepton is quite a bit heavier
than any other lepton lepton I
understand it was I I don't remember
right now what the word lepa Greek
stands for what is it light
not heavy right oh and baryons stand for
heavy you know and meson stand for
something in there that's right Meza
okay the terminology historically was a
little bit confused mesons meant
something in the middle baryons meant
something heavy like protons and
neutrons and leptons meant something
light well because of that the muon was
called the MU meson because it was sort
of midway between the proton and the
electron that terminology went away when
it was realized just how different the
muon was from the PI on which has a
comparable mass to it it was much more
like the electron than it was like the
PI on and so mez arms are now reserved
for quark antiquark pairs and they're
always bosons and muon is no longer ever
called the MU meson so that's just a
historical note okay now what does what
is the probability of this process it
has it's a Fineman diagram every Fineman
diagram has some parts to it and the
parts consist first of all of vertices
and propagators propagators are the
elements which have to do with the
motion of a particle from one point to
another in this particular case the
motion of the w from the point where
it's emitted to the point where the
electron neutrino or electron
antineutrino are created all right so
this process has two main ingredients
that we can isolate from the rest of it
one of them is two powers let's give the
coupling constant the name the coupling
constant for the emission of a w let's
call it G W G either for W boson or for
weak the QCD
the strong interaction coupling constant
for emitting a a gluon we called G
strong this one is G weak as I said it's
a number about the same
order magnitude as the electron charge
so it's not enormous Li small it's not
this it's not the smallness of this
coupling constant which accounts for the
improbable nature of weak interactions
all right so first of all we get two
powers G weak squared that's analogous
to the two powers of electron charge if
we extreme if we exchange a photon this
is expected to be a number of about 1
over 100 it's not exactly the
fine-structure constant it's within a
factor of 3 or something it's close to
the fine-structure constant order
magnitude that's what this is but then
there's something else there is the
propagator of the W boson so we have to
know a little bit about propagators in
quantum field theory they are the
factors which are inserted into a
Fineman diagram to account for the
motion of a particle from one point to
another all right as such they are
simply functions of the space-time
difference of the space-time distance
between the emission and absorption
their functions if you like of the
magnitude or the proper time along
between this event in that event but in
any case they're functions that
propagator let's call it Delta Delta for
a distance between the two points it's a
function of the space-time different
distance between those points function
of distance and it has the following
property it depends crucially on the
mass of the particle that's being
exchanged it depends on the following
way if we what if we were to plot it if
we were to plot it as a function of
distance
now if we went through all the
mathematics of quantum field theory and
worked out the propagator we would find
that it's got a lot of stuff in it it's
got Bessel functions it's a kind of
complicated function but not that
complicated but the important aspect of
it is that it is large at small
distances and falls or grows like one
over the distance to some power went
over the distance squared between the
two points so it's very large at small
distances but then at and if the
particle had no mass it would just
continue on its way with the same power
law fall-off it would just fall off
gradually with one universal behavior
which would go like one over the square
of the distance between the points
that's the way it would be behaved but
the mass of this particle introduces a
new ingredient it introduced as an
ingredient which causes the propagator
to decrease suddenly like that it
decreases exponentially fast
exponentially fast in other words the
power law gives rise to an exponential
and the interesting question is where
does that happen where does that happen
at what value of distance does the mass
suddenly manifest itself and tell a
particle hey you're out there and you
shouldn't be out there because you're
carrying off mass and there's no mass to
carry off I mean you're carrying off
some mass from a UH from there just is
none you've got to get back there that's
but the you know if I think about in
terms of the story the propagator has an
exponential decrease where does it
happen and the answer is just
dimensional analysis in units in which C
equals H bar equals one pick such units
mass mass has the same sorry mass has
the same units now when I write M equals
I simply mean units what's the usual
notation for units to put a square
bracket around the quantity okay
standard notation for the units of an
object that to put a bracket around it a
mass has the same units as an energy
well why is that that's because he
equals MC squared let's see is equal to
1 etc etc but they also have the same
units as inverse length length mass has
the same units as inverse length or or
incidentally is there there's a third
quantity which has the same units of
mass and energy what is it momentum same
as momentum now what about momentum
times distance what are the units of
momentum times distance no uncertainty
uncertainty principle think uncertainty
principle momentum times distance is H
bar but H bar is dimensionless in these
units so momentum and distance simply
have inverse units to each other okay
so therefore length has inverse distance
to both mass energy and also momentum
and therefore we can say that we can
write it differently we can write that
length has units of inverse mass yeah 1
over mass
well that tells us the horizontal axis
here was distance D the mass of the
particle is in and that tells us that
the distance at which it falls off like
this the only way that we can make a
distance using the mass of a particle
occurs at a distance of one over the
mass of the particle now that's really
the the Compton wavelength of the
particle if we put back some C's and H
bars what would it be H bar of MC let's
put back the H bars and H bar over MC
distance of a at a distance of order H
bar over MC the propagator suddenly
dives down and as an exponential the
vertical axis is the size of Delta Delta
and what it is is it's square of the
propagator is the probability that a
particle can go that far before it
before it emits so what this is saying
is that there's a sudden sharp turn off
of the probability for the particle to
go a given distance before converting
like this which is controlled by the
mass of a particle in particular the
heavy of the mass of the particle the
less the distance it can go before it
has to give up its energy in this form
all right now um usually what's
prescribed in an experiment is not the
two points where these events take place
what's prescribed in an experiment is
the momenta of the particles you measure
the momentum of the particles you
measure the momentum of the incident
particle P of the proton note this is
the neutron
down here Neutron you measure the
momentum of the proton and what do you
know
you know the momentum of the W boson the
momentum of the W boson is the
difference of the momentum of the proton
and neutron see another momentum of the
W boson and of course that tells you the
momentum of the electron and neutrino by
momentum conservation you don't as a
rule well certainly not in these kind of
experiments actually no the distance
between those two points
you know the momentum but there's a
relationship between functions of
momentum and functions of position or
functions of distance and that
relationship is Fourier transform you
can think of the propagator either as a
function of positions or momentum you
can think of it as a function of either
position or momentum the position
distance between here and here or the
Fourier transform of this function the
Fourier transform of it is the amplitude
for emitting a W with a given momentum
so the question is what does the Fourier
transform of a function like this look
like I'm not going to work it out this
is something you can go and study for
yourself a function which has a power
law and then a sudden decrease like that
I will simply tell you what the Fourier
transform of the propagator is the
Fourier transform is a function of the
square of the momentum of the W boson
and also parametrically it depends on
the mass of the W boson let's call it
delta twiddle twiddle stands for Fourier
transform and it's a function what
should we call a momentum of the W let's
call it K
what does it look like it's very simple
1 divided by K squared plus the mass of
the W squared
that's it that's the factor that's the
fact that you put in if you know that
momentum of the W and how would you know
it by measuring the initial and final
momentum of the proton and neutron you
measure the momentum of the W and then
you insert this factor in as one of the
factors into the amplitude for the
emission of the W that's the rule
that's fine mins rules and that's it the
addition first of all let's talk about a
photon if we emit a photon it has no
mass and it's just 1 over K squared
typically when you emit a photon in
ordinary quantum electrodynamics the
momentum of the photon is pretty low by
particle physics standards it's
typically you know a few few hundred
electron volts or something like that
it's a very small K and so the
propagator for emitting the photon at
low momentum is rather large at low
momentum this is a big number as K goes
to zero the weak interactions we know
that the probability of emission is much
much smaller as I said it is not the
coupling constant there so the only
thing it can be is the mass of the W
boson if the mass of the W boson is very
large for whatever reason then this is
always going to be small in fact the
biggest it will ever be is what happens
when K is equal to 0 when K is equal to
0 this propagator here is equal to just
1 over M W squared and it's never bigger
than that that's as big as it gets
so the most likely thing to happen is to
emit a low momentum W and if you do it
cost you a probability amplitude equal
to one divided by the mass of the W
squared this is standard quantum field
theory in addition there are the
coupling constants so the net result is
that the probability or the amplitude
not the probability the amplitude for
emitting
a aw and having it convert to an
electron neutrino is GW squared pi
divided by M W squared the MW squared is
the factor in this Fineman diagram for
the W to go from here to here or at
least that's the biggest decay year yeah
there's regular propagator is the K
squared part has minor signs and D not
spread - cables Wow this is true this is
true arm where okay so there we have to
get a little more technical ah and that
mostly comes into play op the the very
little energy is emitted in a situation
like this and more momentum than energy
so it's mostly space like which means
it's positive the reaction you would
have to worry about this if if the
momentum of this was time like but it's
not in these kind of processes but still
the main thing is that it's always small
why is it small a proton becomes in a in
a beta decay the amount of momentum
that's transferred from the proton to
the from the neutron to the proton is
miniscule by comparison with the mass of
the W boson
menisci oh it doesn't even matter
whether it's positive or negative the K
squared it's tiny by comparison with the
with the mass of the W so the net result
is that the weak interactions are made
weak because of the large mass of the W
how large is it about a hundred times
the mass of a proton so that means that
that the amplitude the amplitude for
this process is going to have a factor a
relatively small factor from G W squared
roughly the fine-structure constant and
then a one over m W squared which is a
tiny fraction that's squared the mass of
the W is a hundred times the proton mass
that's a factor of 10,000 but that's
just the amplitude we have to square the
whole thing to find the probability for
the reaction to happen so what does that
mean that means something like G W to
the fourth divided by M W to the fourth
that's a very small number that's a very
small number if the mass of the W is
large
that's why weakened directions are small
not because the primordial coupling
constant is small but because the mass
of the W for whatever reasons happens to
be large in nuclear physics or in proton
Neutron type mass units unusual units of
nuclear physics or old particle physics
the mass of the W is large
well GW squared is about though 10 to
the minus 3 or something and then the
mass of the W is a hundred in proton
units so that's a 10 to the 4 millions
at least from the weakness of the weak
interactions right so right so
originally all it was known from
experiment was this combination what was
known was that combination and it was
called capital G Fermi experimentally
what you measure is neither or by now of
course there are fancier experiments but
the experiments in the old days are
where you never had enough momentum to
make this denominator very very much you
didn't get to see that the mother that
the denominator was was varying with
momentum all you saw was this numerical
constant and it was always the same W
boson in there it didn't change from one
reaction to another there was always the
W boson there's always M W squared and
so experimentally all you knew is this
number G Fermi which is a small number
okay a very small number whatever it's
whatever it's whatever it's numerical
value is its it carries dimensions so if
I told you what is in sum what should I
tell you in units of light-years per
unit
whatever its small number um right so
that's what was known historically some
time in nineteen spin 1950s various
theorist Julian Schwinger other people
began to suspect look maybe the weak
interactions are similar to other
interactions and mediated by some sort
of particle I don't know where that I
don't know where the terminology W came
from probably stood for a week and I
don't know if it was Schwinger or not
who first used it but the idea of a
particle heavy enough that it would make
this a small number was introduced some
time I think in the 50s but it was
recognized pretty much from the
beginning that it would take a pretty
heavy particle a hundred times the mass
of the proton and so it wasn't until
accelerators came into being where you
could generate that much energy
mid 70s late 70s where accelerators
which could create enough energy to
generate a W particle actually detected
it and actually measured it so yeah the
W particle really exists it can be
produced in there now so the beginning
of the class they talked about the
effect of the vining energy which me in
this picture is the presence of
nearby proton suppresses this this whole
process where a Marxist messaging the
president's on the field of the nearby
proton in Europe in other words they
only suppresses it because of energy
conservation nothing else a thing can't
happen if there isn't a better energy
available for it to happen so that's
another thing which controls rates yeah
okay
rates are controlled by three things or
about three things coupling constants
masses of particles in intermediate
states like this and also available
energy available energy has to do with
the energy of the initial state and the
final state there are three different
features coupling constants masses or
propagators if you like the structure of
propagators and how they depend on
momentum and finally a thing can't
happen if there isn't enough energy and
it will happen with very small
probability if the energy available is
small enough so you need the initial
state to have as much energy as the
final state in order for the process to
happen and it's the last of the
ingredients there that had to do with
the suppression of the deuteron decay
reciprocated yeah
these coupling constants are constant
very that we will come to that with
momentum but distance scale yeah well a
real W boson laboratory has a lot of
mass when it degrades into a electron
and a mule whatever right what happens
to that energy the electron the energy
of the final state must be the same as
the energy of the initial state that
means there isn't really enough energy
to create the W boson there really isn't
enough energy to create the W boson
that's why there is no real process in
where a W boson goes flying off there
simply isn't enough energy for that well
so what does happen the W boson is
produced virtually according to the
rules of quantum mechanics a violation
of energy can take place as long as it
takes place for a short enough time if
the amount of extra energy that's in
here let's call it Delta e energy time
uncertainty principle says among other
things that an apparent and apparent
violation of energy conservation Delta e
can only last for a time delta T which
cannot be bigger than just smaller that
in this case clocks constant you cannot
have an apparent violation of energy in
an intermediate state that lasts for a
time longer than Delta e delta T of
water h-bar let me give you another
example of this sort of thing if you
have a potential ordinary potential
energy this potential energy could be
the potential energy of an alpha
particle in a nucleus an alpha particle
is stuck in the nucleus it can't get out
why not
doesn't have enough energy to get out it
has to go over a bump to get out so the
alpha particle normally sits over here
but it can tunnel out quantum
mechanically it can tunnel out now the
kinetic energy of a particle is always
positive right in here it has a certain
amount of energy it has a much higher
potential energy over here this is a
potential a ordinary potential function
the potential energy is up here the
particle started at rest that had no
kinetic energy and had this much
potential energy it has the same amount
of potential energy over here and the
same and is also when it comes out over
here it also comes out of rest comes out
over here at rest was at rest over here
same potential energy same potential
energy so it can happen on the other
hand if you look at it in between it
seems that it had a large potential
energy much larger than it had over here
and it can't have less kinetic energy
that I've had over here the kinetic
energy was over it was zero over here
the meaning of that is that it
temporarily apparently violated energy
conservation now if you went and
measured the particle in here and
checked whether it was in here or not
you would destroy the phenomena of
tunneling but if you just look on the
outside you will have to say somehow in
the intermediate state here the electron
had more energy than it was both alpha
alpha particle had more energy than it
was supposed to have there was a
violation of energy conservation and
apparent one how long can the alpha
particle last under this barrier here
the answer is it can't last long and the
rule is if the violation of energy
conservation
this over here delta e then it had
better get out from under there and a
time delta t which is less than h-bar
over delta e alright so this is a kind
of familiar thing from elementary
quantum mechanics that apparent
violations of energy conservation can
take place as long as they last
sufficiently short time same thing over
here
there is the W boson is a very heavy
particle there is simply not enough
energy in the neutral proton Neutron or
anything else to create a W boson let
alone have enough energy to for the
final particle that cannot happen what
can happen is that temporarily for a
very very short time period the neutron
can emit the w w- become a proton but
then but then it is as if the alpha
particle were under the barrier here the
W boson says I can't last that long I
better get rid of all that energy and it
can do it a number of ways one way it
can do is just by getting reabsorbed
okay the other way I can do it is by
becoming the electron which has a small
energy and the anti neutrino which also
has a small energy so the intermediate
state here of a very very heavy W boson
is very much like the intermediate state
in which the alpha particle is under the
barrier here and it can only last a
short time yeah
any other no no no no and in even energy
conservation from initial to final state
is always exact it's just an apparent
violation
you would have here as though they
reabsorption what happens all the time
basically that fella comes out from the
back
most of the terms are around every once
in a while every once in a billion tries
it was that far enough to reach a itself
that's right that's correct
I've heard most of the time we have a
celebrated caller - really yeah yeah now
the W's will decay to electrons and
neutrinos but if you make a W with
enough energy all right there's a
certain life time for a real W to decay
it's at it's not this it's not this
uncertainty time here there is a certain
life time so the W when it's produced
will eventually decay but the faster the
W is the more time dilation will cause
the W to decay later and later
so real w's are produced and the meaning
of real w's is that you produce things
which whose decay decay probability is
controlled by their velocity in the
standard relativity way ah boy okay
very short very short the W hmm three
times 10 to the 27th - is it true
you said the common constant is the
probability okay how does it translate
into a right or a time for that okay
it's the rate right this this is this is
the amplitude this is the amplitude for
the process the square of the amplitude
is a probability that's this and it's a
probability per unit time it's a
probability per unit time and so it's
inverse is related as related to the
lifetime it's inverse is related to the
lifetime and that's why this is a very
small number the lifetime is unusually
large in particle physics units so weak
lifetimes particles which can only decay
for one reason or another by weak
interactions have anomalously long
lifetimes and where do you trace it to
you trace it to the mass of the W now if
a process remember what this really was
it was K squared plus M W squared ah
well
right if you have enough energy and
enough momentum you can detect the fact
eventually that these rates here will be
momentum dependent in other words the
effective constant here won't be
constant it will depend on K and that of
course has been seen with great
precision
the tunneling process 30 delta-t kind of
velocity zero yeah but if you went in
there and try to detect the velocity you
destroy the cosmos maybe this end and
figure out the distance you can you can
construct something you can call a
velocity it would be misleading to think
of it as the velocity of a real signal
low it's not a signal blossom
we usually get any entertaining the
lifetime of the real w we calculated
this is let's shot so short the W boson
for example it has a number of ways of
the cane but one way it decay can decay
literally decay is into an electron
antineutrino and you can calculate the
Fineman diagram describing it has this
factor G in it W minus a factor G and
electron and antineutrino and you can
calculate that and yes you can compute
the lifetime of the W whatever it is
so sing to us on the question in the
case where in laboratory produce it ugly
goes on what happens to that energy they
look me dead electron that very little
no no the W when a real W decays it
produces an electron neutrino with
enormous kinetic energy very
relativistic right a W boson at rest
will become and there are other decay
modes I mean this is not the only decay
mode I can do a muon and a neutrino and
a number of different decay modes but if
it decayed to an electron neutrino they
would be very very relativistic
electrons virtual real particles are
simply the ones in the created initially
welder the particles which came in and
the particles which went out of a small
interaction region the virtual particles
are mathematical constructs which are
the internal particles in a Fineman
diagram you don't observe them if you
went into the if you if you suddenly try
to observe that particle how would you
observe that particle the only way you
could observe it would be send something
else into the system okay let's let's
talk about trying to observe particles
of this nature or even even before that
what about trying to observe what's
happening to an alpha particle as it
moves under there well obviously you
have only a very short time in to to
observe it so if you want to observe if
you want to know whether there was a
particle under here you would have to
interact with it on a very very short
time scale you know you would have a
very short time scale to get it if you
want to find out for example by looking
at it with a photon you will have to
send in a very very short wavelength
photon pulse
in particular the energy of that photon
pulse would have to be about that big
that's what this energy time uncertainty
principle says the same energy time
uncertainty principle gives you
information about the wavelength and the
energy of a photon that you would need
if you wanted to have a time resolution
good enough to see what was going on in
there all right so if you wanted to
actually see the motion of the alpha
particle from here to here which lasts a
time delta T you would have to hit it
with a photon whose energy was big
enough that it actually would knock the
the alpha particle into this region here
you supply you're supplying the energy
and it's one of these quantum mechanical
complementarity things that you think
something is impossible and so you try
to detect it and you find out in order
to detect it you have to do to the
system exactly that thing which you were
trying to prove does not happen right
this is this is quanta it's it's always
the same story and the same would be
true of virtual particles virtual
particles last a small time if you
wanted to get into the system and detect
one you would have to hit it with
something with enough energy that it
would actually create that particle if
you want to see the virtual W here how
much time you have very short so you hit
it with a photon of photon a
sufficiently small wavelength that guess
what it's got enough energy to actually
knock a W out of the system so you
actually see a W all right that's sort
of unsatisfying and frustrating you were
trying to prove one thing and you found
out that you had to do something to the
system which did to it exactly what
you're trying to prove didn't happen
always that way that's that's quantum
mechanics and much
not true not true if you're trying to
see for example okay so let's let's
first talk about something slightly
different do you ever get to see the
virtual photons that are present in a in
an electron well yeah if you hit the
electron hard enough you'll knock out
though you'll knock the electron out and
the photon will be left over so you do
get to see them in that sense you do get
to see the virtual photons if you do
exactly the experiment which puts in
enough energy to to see those virtual
let's come after the W same thing is
true if you have a proton that proton
can emit it W and become a neutron and
of course if there's nothing else around
that it doesn't decay then the W will
have to come back and be reabsorbed and
so you can think of a proton as a sort
of equilibrium between a proton and a
neutron with the W boson around it
constantly going back and forth between
the two of them between the two things
with a very very very fast oscillation
normally fast oscillation between the
two you want to see that W all you have
to do is hit it hard enough or the
photon that has a frequency which is
large enough that it can resolve the
short times that the W is out there and
guess what if you do hit a proton with a
high energy photon yes you will knock
out W so in that sense you get to see
them but then of course it becomes a
different process it becomes a process
in which the W is a final particle not
an intermediate one
Mongo's the neutron goes to proton you
can also have neutron goes to proton
goes to Neutron with a w the difference
is that this one would be a w+ and this
one would be able to - yes doesn't make
any sense to say that we did that
experiment if you're not going part out
as opposed to you created know you could
say either way yeah
language is one thing facts are another
thing the fact is at the end of the day
there will be a w flying out do you want
to interpret that as a w that was there
beforehand that you knocked out or was
it a newly created w well the
mathematics says that there will be a w
there one picture of it is that the w
was there and you jerked the neutron out
before it before the w had a chance to
get back and the mathematic supports
that i mean that there is a way of
thinking about the mathematics it says
that's what happens on the other hand is
this true if you all you ever get by
putting a definition is w part
well if I play in addition to the double
W particle here I get a double apart
what if I put in twice L energy you
still get down because okay but does not
imply somewhere in existence the W
because you always get double use well
you don't always kick double use
sometimes you get double use sometimes
you get double use sometimes you might
get 3w sometimes you may get when you
hit a particle hard enough you get all
sorts of junk when you hit a particle
really hard this is what I was trying to
tell you the other night you know when
you when you try to think about what is
elementary in what's not elementary it
gets very confusing because if you take
what you thought was a very elementary
particle
and you hit it really hard enough all
kinds of junk comes out and among the
junk that comes out might be chairs and
tables well you'd need a hell of a lot
of energy for that but you hit an
electron hard enough with a photon
really really really hard meaning to say
with much much more energy than for
example a mass of a proton mass or a
thousand protons for example and guess
what out of it will come protons
electrons all sorts of things every once
in a while one of those electrons will
stick to a proton and so you will
discover that inside an electron or
inside a proton is there's a hydrogen
atom the lesson is don't try to your
your mental picture of what comes out of
a system is necessarily what was in
there beforehand it's a little bit
different this in itself doesn't this in
itself doesn't the vacuum energy really
has to do with diagrams which are
disconnected from the rest of just
they're in the vacuum but the presence
of vacuum diagrams like this
okay so a vacuum diagram is something
which also viola apparently violates
energy conservation let's suppose this
were an electron an electron of the
photon two electrons necessarily have a
certain minimum amount of energy the
vacuum has no energy okay and so there's
a certain violation of energy in there
that means that that pair can only last
for a short time and say okay I would
like to see that pair so you send in
some very high frequency photon or a
pair of very high frequency photons from
opposite sides and guess what you
sometimes make electron positron pairs
with extra photon in them so you knock
the hell out of that vacuum fluctuation
and you discover you discover pairs
apart
oh no they're not dependent on
temperature they are dependent on the
particles that you're colliding having a
lot of energy all right so it's a good
question let's say what it has to do
with temperature when you have a system
at high temperature it simply means that
you have a lot of particles around with
high energy so that means that typically
at high temperatures there are enough
high energy particles to cause these
things to happen but just think of high
temperatures just having a lot of high
energy particles around if you have a
very small number of high energy
particles you won't think of that as
temperature you'll just say I have some
particles with large kinetic energy an
example of what temperature can do is if
you have the alpha particle bound inside
the nucleus like that and then you put
it into a temperature bath now I don't
mean a tempura I don't mean your bath
water temperature bath I mean
temperatures which are many M V's high
which is zillions and zillions of
degrees high but the effect of putting
it into temperature you can either think
of it as particles coming in and
colliding or you can just think of it as
thermal vibrations causing this alpha
particle to jiggle around and give it
enough temperature and sure enough it
will jiggle over the top sometimes so
yes these virtual processes can be
induced by temperature but temperature
is another way of just saying there's a
lot of high-energy particle
did you say that the vacuum could not be
attributed to the generation W plus T
the practice they are contributed
variable subtracting talked about the
dark incorporations vacuum fluctuation
the W entices some kind of a fluctuation
to vision without using partner without
using part I know it did but is there a
relationship between the W the W in this
diagram is a fluctuation but it's not a
fluctuation of a vacuum it's a
fluctuation of the proton the proton
sometimes fluctuates and makes a w and a
neutron that's you know a relative of
but not the same thing as saying arm and
electron a anti neutrino and aw let's
see that would be a w+ can sometimes
form a vacuum fluctuation it's another
process where there really isn't enough
energy for it to happen so what happens
in this virtual sense for a short period
of time and in that sense it's similar
to this but it's different but the same
rules apply to it it can only last for a
short time therefore if you want to get
into it and observe it you have to do it
with something which has very high
energy because of the uncertainty
principle and the result is the energy
is always enough if you if the energy is
high enough to see in there it'll also
be high enough to create those particles
you have enough energy actually really
sir
through the antineutrino is necessary
there conservationists fear yeah mm-hmm
but another way of saying it is that the
basic interaction is always be one
between electron neutrino and W all
right but yes it is
good coffee eat into a cake chocolate
cake body
well basically have an energy Wow just
one taco why only one chocolate cake
okay so how much what's the weight of a
chocolate cake weight of a chocolate
cake is if it's really good chocolate
cake dense it weighs a kilogram right
all right a kilogram is thousand grams
which is ten to the 8th plunk masses
okay 10 to the 8th plunk masses that's
right if you could accelerate a pair of
particles to 10 to the 8th plunk masses
with a very very very small probability
you might get a chocolate cake out dream
on Michael
or anything else
Dumpty's pull up using your charity if
you get electron is turning into chair
anti chair currently now if you take
that to an extreme shortest possible
time what would it be to mast out like a
plant over Parkman yes the point mass
which is about 10 to the minus 5 grams
no no the clock mass is not the heaviest
mass obviously not in touch here's a
shorter time plate planets and anti
planets galaxies powers if you collide
particles and energies much larger than
the plunk mass what you get I was going
to say 99 times out of 100 but let's
make it 99.999 endlessly out of or
whatever it is you'll get a black hole
okay but every once in a while with a
probability which is exponentially small
in the entropy of the black hole that
black hole will emit a chair instead
right how do I know that I know that
because the process of a chair falling
into a black hole as proud as possible
and therefore by time reversal
invariance the process of a black hole
emitting a chair must be possible so yes
every once in a while the black hole or
when I say every once in a while I mean
a very rare percentage of the times that
you do this experiment the black hole
will behave and a statistically
extremely unlikely way but all that
entropy is is statistics and basically
anything that can happen will happen
eventually and so yes everything can
come out of a black hole if you do the
process enough times so above so all of
this above the Planck energy scale has
to do with the proposition from black
hole virtual photons and then your
vehicles are bosons while they interact
with jelly bosons and post buying
individual virtual photons and virtual
will a language any other virtual Photon
okay virtual processor you directly well
save is another dummy with closed hiding
virtual W if they were the quality of
thing is above silence you want to know
- mm-hmm
your question well down a solid NC
state probabilistic
interact with each other no Lisa no
photons do interact with each other a
little bit
you know how they interact with each
other the fact that they're bosons is
not what says that they don't interact
with each other all zones fermions they
all interact no difference in that
respect the reason that the photon
doesn't seem to interact with other
photons let's let's see if we can trace
it down photons can scatter now
ordinarily in the laboratory two light
beams on scatter each other but two
photons can do the following a photon
can come in another photon can come in
and they can create an electron-positron
pair electron minus E Plus
electron-positron pair well if that can
happen then the opposite can happen an
electron-positron pair can become a pair
of photons and in fact it can happen as
a virtual process as a virtual process
and a lot of para photons can come in
and go out but scatter by means of an
intermediate state which is an
electron-positron pair okay now why
doesn't it happen in the laboratory with
ordinary photons and the answer is it
takes a certain though it takes a
certain amount of energy to create the
electron positron pairs right each
electron has a mass of what is it half
an MeV right just so these together take
an MeV of energy if the pair of photons
has energy very very much lower than
that then there is not enough energy for
the real creation of an
electron-positron pair but still it can
happen virtually but when it happens
virtually there are propagators in here
the same sort of deal as what happened
here when you have to supply extra
energy for the process to happen there
is always a cost in probability
typically the cost and probability is
somehow inverse to the amount of energy
that that you need to make the process
happen okay so this process doesn't
happen in the laboratory because in the
laboratory photon energies are always
vastly smaller than the mass of an
electron photon energies are what an
electron volt typical photon optical
photons are electron volta to the mass
of an electron is of order a million
electron volts and so typically the
photons don't have nearly enough energy
for this process to happen and when a
process when an intermediate process
happens which has to happen very fast it
comes and goes it's always at a cost of
probability so this process the
scattering is a very low probability
process at low energies on the other
hand if the photons hit with enough
energy to be able to create an
electron-positron pair they really do
interact with each other now I forget
what the original question was it had to
do with W bosons but the same thing same
thinking is true W bosons do interact
with each other I wasn't talking about
that type of interaction as talking
about
their statistical interaction because oh
they are bosons yes don't think it's not
an interaction it's just effective
beause of statistics um well let's put
it this way the effects of the
statistics fermion versus boson is only
interesting when you have a situation
where you create more than one particle
so more than one particle pretty well
knew each other pretty much in the same
state in most particle physics
experiments you create the particles
going off flying off in every direction
and it's very rare that you have two
particles of the same type going off and
pretty much the same direction in such a
way that it matters very much with the
fermions or bosons but yes I mean they
do interact statistically the same way
photons do W bosons will prefer to be in
the same state in the same sense the
photons preferred in principle you could
make a laser out over them don't the not
likely but in principle you could make a
system lays W bosons
if you call a weaver with color is no
it's oh no it's always three quarks one
red one green and one blue which makes
it white or colorless a black or white
I'm not sure but then
there's superpositions of some but the
proton is always wondered for green one
or is this earth place to bring out what
happens at the other end of the energy
spectrum like the bose-einstein
condensate where is that question is
this a place to fit it in or will we get
to it yeah we will get to it and we'll
get to it in the context of the Higgs
boson yeah
the Higgs boson is a place where
something like bozer condensation
happens all right I did have one nobody
has asked me so let me bring it up
myself what kind of group structure
could we imagine which would mix the up
quark in the down quark oh the up quark
and a down quark the charm quark and the
strange co-op just forget them just up
quark and down quark they go into each
other by W emission what group could we
be talking about how it's obvious we're
talking about su 2 there are two
elements here and one can go to the
other
that's the symmetry of the of the system
we're talking about us you two but how
many generators is this you to have good
has three generators each generator the
gauge bosons are in one-to-one
correspondence with the with the
generators in the group that's the way
it works the eight gauge bosons the
eight gluons there's one for each
generator of su 2 su 3 we only have two
gauge bosons W + + W - but we're trying
to postulate that this is a theory based
on the symmetry su - we're missing
something
and indeed we are we're missing one
gauge boson it is not the photon it is
not the Photon
it is closely related to the particle
called the Z boson on third member of
the W family W plus W minus and Z okay
we'll come to it next time please remind
me if I forget to talk about the
relationship between electric charge Z
boson su 2 and so forth we've got to
come to that but I wasn't I was going to
talk about it but it's getting too late
for now in fact it's getting a little
too late to do almost anything the other
thing I had intended to talk about
tonight was spontaneous symmetry
breaking let's talk a little bit about
spontaneous symmetry breaking just
qualitatively and we won't try to do
anything quantitative tonight just
qualitatively what is spontaneous
symmetry breaking
I think the best way to describe it is
by illustrating it
there's a famous illustration which is
in a sense spontaneous symmetry breaking
but if it helps you okay it does it's
actually somewhat correct the famous
example is people sit down to dinner and
around the large table and each person
has to the left of them a fork and to
the right of them a fork next person
left to them and rather than a fork and
nobody knows whether to go for the left
fork for the left for left fork or the
right fork and they sit there and they
sit there and they sit there and they
can't decide what to do until all of a
sudden one of them looks a little motion
toward the right fork and then they all
go for the right fork
there was nothing asymmetric to begin
with but there was a kind of instability
there was a kind of instability two
possibilities an instability and the
instability being such that when the
instability is kicked off the whole
universe so to speak suddenly goes one
way instead of the other way so I will
give you an example mathematical example
a ferromagnet is an example of
spontaneous symmetry breaking but let's
think let's start with a very simple
example the simple example is a bunch of
spins and the spins can either be all up
or all sorry the spins can either be up
or down for the moment it's not even
important that we're talking about
quantum mechanics these could be coins
classical coins and um the coins can
either be up or down
they laid out on the table in a lattice
there they are and as an interaction
energy between neighboring coins the
interaction energy is such that if a
coins if the neighbors are opposite for
example a heads and a tails that cost
energy in other words there's some kind
of force between the particles or the
spins or the coins so that if they're
opposite that costs some energy if
they're parallel it costs less energy so
they like to be parallel energetically
if they like to be parallel but parallel
can mean this way or this way anti
parallel can mean this way or this way
anti parallel cost more energy than
parallel okay now think about the state
of lowest energy what is the state of
lowest energy the state of lowest energy
is obviously all heads or all tails
there are two states of lowest energy
all heads are all tails which one is the
ground state
they're both ground States but now
supposing way far away off a hundred
miles away one of the spins is known to
be heads that one is asymmetric well
normally under most circumstances you
would say that one degree of freedom
very very far away has no effect on what
the properties of the ground state are
far away from that degree of freedom
that's a typical expectation it's
usually true it's almost always true
ordinarily but in this case that one
head will cause the ground state energy
to be different if they're all heads
than earth or all tails if they're all
heads then you'll save one unit of
energy and so in seeking its ground
state this
we'll tend to all heads rather than all
tails
once it's all heads then you can forget
you can once it's all heads then you can
start over again and say look the lowest
energy state of the system is all heads
it will cost me some energy to put a
tail in there because it has four
neighbors which are trying to make it a
head so the result is that this kind of
system although it started with a
symmetry it started with the symmetry
heads goes to tails and asymptotically
very very far away boundary conditions
or just a very very distant degree of
freedom will tip off a instability and
put the system into one of the many
possible in this case only two possible
ground states and once it's in that
ground state then the properties of what
goes on in here are determined by that
ground state in particular a tail will
cost you energy because of the presence
of all the heads this is the simple and
a primitive most primitive example of a
spontaneous symmetry breaking how is it
different than just an ordinary symmetry
breaking what would an ordinary symmetry
breaking be mean an ordinary symmetry
breaking or we can call an explicit
symmetry breaking would be a symmetry
breaking if heads had a different energy
than tails not pairwise energies but
just one head by itself supposing that
one head by itself had less energy than
a tail then of course it would be
completely obvious that the system would
in its lowest energy state be all heads
and so it would be also the case all
heads but there would be no second
ground state in which they were all
tails it would be biased by the energy
we'll be biased by the energy not the
one extra particle infinitely far away
but by the local things going on near
body okay so that would be a a bias
situation where heads and tails were not
equivalent to each other
we're not energetically the same and
it's not a spontaneous symmetry breaking
it's just no symmetry to begin with or
an explicit symmetry breaking is there
any difference between explicit symmetry
breaking and spontaneous symmetry
breaking yes there is there is one
phenomena that can happen when there's
spontaneous symmetry breaking that will
not happen if there's explicit symmetry
breaking the phenomenon is called domain
walls a domain wall is what happens if
far away out here very very far away you
insist along this line here that
everybody is heads now way out here
you'll assume that everybody is tails
what then is the state of lowest energy
and then the state of lowest energy is
everybody on the side tails everybody on
the side heads and a boundary in between
we're heads go from two we're tails go
too far from the boundary where you go
from tails - heads called domain wall so
the presence of domain wall and this
would not be the case if you had
explicit symmetry breaking if you had
explicit symmetry breaking then the
state of lowest energy would just be all
heads period wouldn't care that they
wouldn't care very much that you did
this thing over here so spontaneous
symmetry breaking in this case the
signal of it is the existence under
certain circumstances certain kinds of
experimental setups would lead to the
existence of domain walls where on one
side you had one thing on the other side
you had the other thing and so it would
be the presence of domain walls which
would be the signal that there was a
spontaneous symmetry breaking alright so
this is the basic idea of spontaneous
symmetry breaking a symmetry of the
system but with an instability or a
instability that you can kick off by
going very far away and just fiddling
with something very far away and that
will fix everything as I said the signal
or the signature of it is the existence
of domain walls next time we'll talk
about other kinds of spontaneous
symmetry breaking and come to the higgs
phenomenon the Higgs phenomena is a
phenomenon of spontaneous symmetry
breaking and we'll talk about it next
time so just keep just keep this example
in mind for more please visit us at
stanford.edu